{"tossups": [{"question": "One side\u2019s plans in this battle were almost revealed by a premature attack from Adam Stephen. The losing side of this battle had earlier been weakened by the departure of Carl von Donop\u2019s men. The password \u201cvictory or death\u201d was used in this battle, in which Johann Rall was mortally wounded. A famous painting by Emanuel Leutze [loyt-zah] depicts how the winning side in this battle crossed the Delaware River on Christmas Eve. For ten points, name this Revolutionary War battle in which George Washington surprised the Hessians.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Trenton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was demoted after he took the advice of the spy Yoshira and refused to attack. In a strait near Jindo Island, this man\u2019s dozen ships fended off Todo Takatora\u2019s much larger fleet. This man was killed by a stray arquebus bullet in the Battle of Noryang, during the later stages of the Imjin War. This admiral lost no ships in the Battle of Myeongnyang. Turtle ships defended the Joseon kingdom against Toyotomi Hideyoshi under, for ten points, what 16th century Korean naval commander?", "answer": "<b> Yi</b> Sun-sin", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. In 1993, one of these events was organized by Susan Sontag under candlelight only. The documentary<em> The Impossible Itself</em> is about two of these events, held at Luttringhausen and San Quentin prisons. One of these events prominently featured a tree designed by Alberto Giacometti, and the first of these events was witnessed by less than one hundred people in a Paris theater in 1953. For ten points, identify these events in which an absurdist work of Samuel Beckett is shown.", "answer": "<b> Productions of</b><em><b> Waiting for Godot</b></em> (accept synonyms for production, such as<b> staging</b> or <b>performance</b>; prompt on partial answers, such as \u201c(putting on a) play\u201d and \u201c(putting on a) play by Samuel Beckett\u201d before his name is mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "This country ceded the southern part of Dobruja to its southern neighbor in the Treaty of Craiova. Another region of this country, Szekely [see-kay] Land, has a large Hungarian-speaking population. A revolution in this country started in Timisoara [tim-ee-shor-uh] in 1989, and it traces its modern history to the 1859 unification of the principalities of Wallachia and Moldavia. This country is separated from Transylvania by the Carpathian Mountains. Vlad the Impaler once lived in, for ten points, what country with capital Bucharest?", "answer": "<b> Romania</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Hawksbill Creek Agreement guarantees that a planned city in this country enjoys no taxation; that city of Freeport on this country\u2019s \u201cGrand\u201d island is now a prominent tourist hub. During the Civil War, blockade runners left from Charleston to this country\u2019s port of Nassau. For ten points, name this member of the British Commonwealth, an island chain just east of Florida and northeast of Cuba.", "answer": "(Commonwealth of) The<b> Bahamas</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This ruler executed Helvidius Priscus for defending the Senate\u2019s right to manage state finances. This ruler\u2019s bid for power was supported by Mucianus, the governor of Syria. This ruler worked with Agricola in the pacification of Britain, and he became the patron of historian Josephus, who he met while suppressing the Great Jewish Revolt. Shortly after the death of Nero, this man succeeded Vitellius to end the Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this father of Titus and founder of the Flavian dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Vespasian</b> (or Titus Flavius<b> Vespasian</b>us; do not accept or prompt on Titus)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man resisted his initial calling, saying that he was too young to speak; when he did begin his ministry, the people of his hometown tried to kill him, for which God promised destruction on the town of Anathoth. Near the end of his life, this man was forcibly taken to Egypt with his scribe Baruch, who recorded this man\u2019s sayings into a namesake book. For ten points, name this Israelite, often called the\u201cweeping prophet,\u201d the author of the Book of Lamentations.", "answer": "<b> Jeremiah</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "An introductory quote made by this man titles a book chronicling his activities,<em> I Heard You Paint</em> <em>Houses</em>. This man rose to power by organizing support for Dave Beck. A prison sentence that this man received for illegally distributing pension funds was commuted by Richard Nixon in 1971. After eating at the Machus Red Fox restaurant outside of Detroit, this man vanished mysteriously in 1975. For ten points, name this thirteen-year president of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters.", "answer": "James \u201cJimmy\u201d<b> Hoffa</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 2010, this city\u2019s Park Kultury metro stop was suicide-bombed by two women working for Doku Umarov. Special forces were criticized for indiscriminately killing 130 civilians with poison gas while trying to resolve a hostage crisis in a theatre in this city. In 1999, FSB agents were accused of staging false flag apartment bombings upon this capital city in order to justify the Second Chechen War. For ten points, name this capital of the Russian Federation.", "answer": "<b> Moscow</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This composer dedicated his song \u201cThe Little Brook\u201d to Joseph Goebbels and wrote an<em> Olympic</em> <em>Hymn</em> that premiered at the 1936 Berlin Olympics. This composer used both a D clarinet and the French horn to represent the title trickster in his tone poem<em> Till Eulenspeigel\u2019s Merry Pranks</em>. A C-G-C motif opens the \u201cSunrise\u201d section of another tone poem by this composer, based on a book by Friedrich Nietzsche [nee-cha]. For ten points, name this composer of<em> Also Sprach Zarathustra</em>.", "answer": "<b> R</b>ichard<b> Strauss</b> (prompt on Strauss alone)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s forces blundered by shooting Hayward Shepherd in the view of train passengers, who then alerted authorities. An earlier group led by this man attempted to kill Dutch Henry in the Pottawatomie Massacre during Bleeding Kansas. The Battle Hymn of the Republic was set to the tune of a song about the body of this man, who was hanged for attacking a federal armory. For ten points, name this radical abolitionist who launched an 1859 raid on Harpers Ferry.", "answer": "John<b> Brown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This country indicted Tatsuya Kato for his reporting of the aftermath of a 2013 disaster that killed 304 people, including numerous students from Danwon High School. Wikileaks released a 2007 diplomatic cable in which this country\u2019s current president was accused of being under the control of a \u201cRasputin\u201d like figure. Choi Soon-sil faces charges of influencing Park Geun-Hye, the president of, for ten points, what Asian country where protesters against Park flooded the streets of Seoul?", "answer": "<b> South Korea</b> (or<b> R</b>epublic<b> o</b>f<b> K</b>orea)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Allen Klein\u2019s brief leadership of this company is often cited as a contributing factor for the band\u2019s breakup.", "answer": "<b> Apple</b> Corps, Inc. (accept<b> Apple</b> Publishing and/or<b> Apple</b> Records; do not accept Apple Music, as that\u2019s the iTunes people instead)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A political cartoon of this man depicts him urging his soldiers to fight while sitting on the mast of a boat with a telescope. This man rose to fame after a victory against Robert Garnett at Rich Mountain. He ran on a ticket with George Pendleton, though the capture of Atlanta hurt his peace platform in a presidential campaign. This man was removed from command after failing to pursue Robert E. Lee\u2019s troops after a victory at Antietam. For ten points, name this overly-cautious Union general who ran against Lincoln in the 1864 election.", "answer": "George<b> McClellan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This leader\u2019s Anti-Radical Decree prevented communists from taking jobs as teachers. In the midst of negotiating the boundaries of the Oder-Neisse line with Poland, this leader</b> <b>performed the</b><em><b> kniefall</b></em><b> [\u201dkneefall\u201d] in front of a (+)</b> <b>monument to victims of the Warsaw</b> <b>Ghetto Uprising. This Social Democrat was forced to resign when his aide, Gunter Guillaume [ghee-ohm], was revealed to be a (*)</b> Stasi agent from a neighboring country. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who won the 1971 Nobel Peace Prize for his practice of<em> ostpolitik</em>.", "answer": "Willy<b> Brandt</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This scientist worked with Pierre-Simon Laplace on a work read to the Royal Academy of Sciences,</b><em><b> Memoir on Heat</b></em><b>. He discovered that respiration is a form of combustion and</b> <b>that diamonds are composed of carbon. Works by this chemist include his (+)</b> <em><b>Essays</b></em> <em><b>Physical and Chemical</b></em><b> and his</b><em><b> Elementary Treatise on Chemistry</b></em><b>. This chemist named oxygen and hydrogen and disproved the phlogiston theory; he also developed the law of conservation of mass before (*) </b> losing his head to the guillotine. For ten points, name this French scientist, often considered the father of modern chemistry.", "answer": "Antoine<b> Lavoisier</b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "<b>One of this artist\u2019s works was inspired by the Zong massacre. This artist requested that he be buried in the canvas of his work showing the title character across from the tomb of</b> <b>Sychaeus [sih-KAY-us]. This \u201cpainter of light\u201d and artist of (+)</b> <em><b>Dido Building Carthage</b></em> <b>obscured Hannibal\u2019s army in one of two works titled Snow-Storm. In the 1840s, he painted the (*)</b> Maidenhead Railway Bridge with a train barreling toward the viewer. For ten points, name this painter of<em> Slave Ship</em> and<em> Rain, Steam, and Speed</em>.", "answer": "J(oseph) M(allord) W(illiam)<b> Turner</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>A woman who married into this family was indigo developer Eliza Lucas. A member of this family was the unsuccessful running mate of John Adams in the election of 1800, and earlier shouted \u201cNo, no, not a sixpence!\u201d during the XYZ Affair alongside John Marshall</b> <b>and (+)</b> <b>Elbridge Gerry. Another member of this family negotiated a very popular treaty</b> <b>guaranteeing the U.S. navigational rights on the Mississippi River; that 1791 treaty was with (*) </b> Spain. Charles Cotesworth and Thomas were part of, for ten points, what prominent early South Carolina family?", "answer": "<b> Pinckney</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The court of this king resolved a disputation in which Nicholas Donin pressed charges of blasphemy against the Talmud. This king allowed Henry III to keep his conquests in</b> <b>Aquitaine despite defeating him at (+)</b> <b>Taillebourg. During a campaign, this king was</b> <b>captured by the troops of Baibars and Qutuz. Damietta was given to the Mamluks in exchange for the release of this king following the Battle of Al-Mansurah. This king died of dysentery in modern-day (*) </b> Tunisia while leading the Eighth Crusade. For ten points, name this only French monarch to be canonized.", "answer": "<b> Louis IX</b> (or<b> Saint Louis</b>; prompt on Louis)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The principles of </b><em><b>pancasila</b></em><b> inspired this country\u2019s (*)</b> \u201cNew Order,\u201d which replaced the idea of \u201cGuided Democracy.\u201dFor ten points, name this Southeast Asian country whose president Suharto invaded East Timor.", "answer": "<b> Indonesia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man consolidated power in one union by forcing rivals to listen to peer abuse in a process known as \u201cthe Game.\u201d In an attempt to drum up support from Filipinos, this man</b> <b>made the mistake of meeting with Ferdinand Marcos, leading to a break with (+)</b> <b>Philip</b> <b>Vera Cruz. This man utilized the motto \u201cSi, se puede\u201d [see, say pway-day] during a hunger strike and joined the Delano (*)</b> grape march on Sacramento to fight for higher wages for laborers. For ten points, name this Mexican-American activist who helped found the United Farm Workers.", "answer": "C\u00b4esar<b> Ch\u00b4avez</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>This man agreed to the Panchsheel Treaty and the Five Principles of Peaceful</b> <b>Coexistence with a country he called \u201cbrothers.\u201d His \u201cForward Policy,\u201d designed to</b> <b>create bases past the McMahon Line, led to a failed war with (+)</b> <b>China. This man</b> <b>was a rival of the leader of the Muslim League, Muhammad Ali Jinnah, and signed</b> <b>the London Declaration regarding his country\u2019s status in the Commonwealth. The (*)</b> Indian National Congress was once led by, for ten points, what follower of Mahatma Gandhi and first Prime Minister of India? ANSWER: Jawaharlal<b> Nehru</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}